<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable discourse written by Mr. Iohn Dury upon the earnest requests of many, briefly shewing these particulars 1. What the grounds and method of our reformation ought to be in religion and learning. 2. How even in these times of distraction, the worke may be advanced. By the knowledge of Orientall tongues and Jewish mysteries. By an agency for advancement of universall learning. Published by Samuel Hartlib. Aprill 24. 1649. Imprimatur Joseph Caryl.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E579_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859894</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 89:E579[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable discourse written by Mr. Iohn Dury upon the earnest requests of many, briefly shewing these particulars 1. What the grounds and method of our reformation ought to be in religion and learning. 2. How even in these times of distraction, the worke may be advanced. By the knowledge of Orientall tongues and Jewish mysteries. By an agency for advancement of universall learning. Published by Samuel Hartlib. Aprill 24. 1649. Imprimatur Joseph Caryl.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Woodnothe, at the Starre under Peters Church in Corne-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hartlib, Samuel, d. 1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Education --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Learning and scholarship --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Seaſonable DISCOURSE Written by Mr. Iohn Dury UPON The earneſt requeſts of many, briefly ſhewing theſe Particulars</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> What the Grounds and Method of our Reformation ought to be in Religion and Learning.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> How even in theſe times of diſtraction, the Worke may be advanced.</item>
               </list> By the knowledge of <hi>Orientall</hi> tongues and Jewiſh Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. By an Agency for advancement of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Publiſhed, By SAMUEL HARTLIB.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>Aprill <hi>24. 1649.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> R. Woodnothe, <hi>at the</hi> Starre <hi>under</hi> Peters <hi>Church in</hi> Corne-hill. <hi>1649.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:111996:2"/>
            <head>An Extract out of the Humble Addreſſes of the free and Wel-affected People, and Inhabitants of the County and City of LINCOLN. To his Excellency the L. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and his Generall Councell of War. Inſerted into the PERFECT DIURNALL. <hi>Numb.</hi> 296. <hi>pag.</hi> 2372.</head>
            <p>THat ſome Publick Schools for the better education and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling of youth in vertue and juſtice, would ſoberly be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of and fettled, that ſo by not leaving them looſe to themſelves, and their careleſſe Parents (the Laws being defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to inſtruct them well when Children, though not to puniſh them for it when men) they may not remaine lyable, to be ſcourged for the faults of their naturall and civill Parents rather then their own, as they now do. Beſides that, according to the ſtructure this Generation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to build for the next, it may not againe incline to fall by its own weight, through negligence of timely preparing fit materials to ſupport and confirme it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111996:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF REFORMATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are upon the deſigne of a Publick Reformation, herein every body is one way or other, if not engaged yet concerned, ſome more ſome leſſe, ſome in a private; ſome in a Publicke way. This work hath been long in hand, many ſtones have been moved about it, much duſt is raiſed in it; and to the outward appearance af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all attempts, we are further from our purpoſe then at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; For their is more viſible oppoſition, and leſſe inclination to a ſettlement then ever; ſo that we muſt expect (if God in mercy doth not prevent it) that the Publick profeſſion of Religion (the Sunne ſhine of our ſoul) will be turned into darknes, and the outward Government of the State (the Moone which ſhineth upon our civill converſation) will be changed into blood.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not here look backward, to enquire into the cauſes which have obſtructed our hopefull proceedings; for that may beget more, and not cure any of our diſtempers; but we ſhall rather look forward, and after ſome grounds of Councells, which either now, or hereafter (when ever God ſhall make it ſeaſonable) may give to the Maſter-Builders oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to lay the foundations of their building more deeply, and build therupon more ſolidly then is ordinarily intended, or at leſt they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come happily in their hand ſome help towards their work, by preventing or rectifying ſome of the cauſes of our cheif diſeaſes; which originally proceed from Ignorance, and from ſelf-ſeeking partiality.</p>
            <p>The Ignorance is of the true aime; and rules of proceeding towards an effectuall Reformation.</p>
            <p>The Partiality and ſelf-ſeeking is about the uſe of the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that aime is to be proſecuted.</p>
            <p>Now then, that ſomething towards the removall of theſe evils, by the ſuggeſtion of ſome poſitive and unqueſtionable principles, may be offet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in brief to the unpartiall Lovers of Truth and Righteouſnes, we ſhall endeavour to open the matter of theſe two Queſtions.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111996:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>The firſt, <hi>What is meant by the Publick good?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond, <hi>How the Publick good ought to be advanced?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And this we ſhall do (God willing) in a few propoſitions, to the end that ſuch as ſhall be pleaſed to examine ſeriouſly, and lay to heart conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably the ſence thereof, may have occaſion (if they will enlarge their thoughts thereon) to draw by their own judgements ſome ſatisfactory concluſions; which may ſet forward the deſignes of that Reformation which ſhould be endeavoured, and wherunto we ſhall herein contribute ſome of our beſt wiſhes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the firſt Queſtion. <hi>What a Publick Good is?</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. No man can be ſaid truly to aime at, or to proſecute a Publick good. except he underſtand the true principles of that which is good in it ſelfe and to us, and of that which is publickly ſo, and then alſo except he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed anſwerably thereunto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The true principle of that which is good in it ſelf and to us, can be no thing elſe, but the known purpoſe of Gods will towards mankind: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none is good in himſelf ſave God alone; and towards us nothing is found good, acceptable and perfect, but what is according to his will. Rom. 12.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The purpoſe of his will towards mankind is this; that Man ſhould be with God, to enjoy him, and have communion with him in all things, which is now and for ever all his happines.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To bring this purpoſe to paſſe, God hath appointed meanes whereby he doth offer himſelf unto Man, and whereby Man is fitted to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This meanes is, <hi>The Grace which bringeth ſalvation in Jeſus Chriſt, which God hath made appear to all men; that they ſhould deny ungodlineſſe and worldy luſts, and live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The fitting of Man to come unto God by this Grace is, when Faith is begotten in him by the <hi>acknowledgment of the truth which is after godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> and when godlines is effectually perfected in him, by the ſpirit of Regeneration in the life of Love and holines.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If therefore a Man do attaine to that which the good will of God hath appointed for him, and whereby he is fitted to have communion with God, then he is partaker of that which is good indeed; but if he doth not attaine to this, nothing can be good unto him, becauſe he doth miſſe of his cheif &amp; only end, and of the meanes thereof; without which he cannot be happy in any thing.</p>
               <p n="8">8. This then is that which is to be counted good, in a direct and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111996:3"/>ſenſe; and every thing elſe is good, as it is reducible hereunto, and not otherwiſe. And thus much of that which is the Principle of Good.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The true Principle of that which is publickly good, is nothing elſe but the right way of Common Nature; whereby Man being more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then other Creatures, is obliged to do all things as Man, and for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; For every thing is to act ſutable to its own nature and kind.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The way wherein Common Nature hath ſet Man, is that he ſhould lead, rule, and employ all things to their common ends, and not that he ſhould be lead, ruled, or employed by them in any thing.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The way whereby Man is enabled to do all things as Man is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. and whereby he may do all for Mankind is ſociety; For by that alone Man is Man, and by this onely, all things are made uſefull unto all men.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Reaſon is in man the faculty of his mind, by which he is enabled to know and judge to order and direct himſelf, his own actions, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things belonging to his own or their being, towards the ends and uſes, for which God hath fitted both him and them, to the enjoyment of the happines whereof he and they are capable.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Society in Man, is upon the intereſt which one man hath in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he is rationall, a freedom to joyn in endeavours, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with, and to communicate unto him all things to a Common Good.</p>
               <p>The ground then of humane ſociety is Reaſon, the way of it is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Action according to Reaſon, and the end, both of ſociety and reaſon is the common enjoyment of good things.</p>
               <p>If a man therefore do ſet himſelf in the way of humanity above other things of the world, to uſe them freely as common Servants, that they may be rationally imployed towards the attainment of that which is the good of all; then he doth indeed aime at that which is publickly good. But if he doth not ſet himſelf in this way, although his actions be never ſo ſpecious, his pretences never ſo faire, and his works materially never ſo compleat; yet his aime is only at himſelf, and when he ſhall be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give an account of that Stewardſhip wherein the publique good hath been intruſted unto him: he will be found unfaithfull in his truſt, a cheater of himſelf in that which is good, and a robber of others in that which is publique.</p>
               <p>From all which this is to be inferred, that as no man without piety and the right uſe of reaſon can be happy; ſo no humane ſociety without the advancement of theſe two unto the Members thereof, can enjoy that which is either truly good, or truly publique. For as out of the way of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111996:4"/>godlineſs there can be no enjoyment of God unto happineſs: So out of the way of right Reaſon there can be no common intereſt unto a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we may find by experience, that the way of piety begets grace, and the uſe of Reaſon Induſtry, as in one man, ſo in a whole Nation; but if the meanes to propagate grace inwardly, and ſtirre up Induſtry outwardly ſhould be neglected in a Nation, how can any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good be hoped for therein? we muſt conclude therefore, that as in reference to God, grace, and in reference to man, Induſtry, are the two hands, whereby every one for himſelf doth receive the bleſſings of all eternall and temporall proſperity: So piety towards God, and the uſe of right Reaſon amongſt men, are the effectuall moving faculties, whereby theſe hands are ſtretched out and ſet a working both to God and men, for the good of a publique Society.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſecond Queſtion. <hi>How the publique good ought to be advanced?</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. SEeing we have found by the foregoing diſquiry, that piety &amp; the right uſe of reaſon, are the undoubted Fountains of all that is to be accounted publickly good, inſtead of this ſecond generall Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How the publique good ought to be advanced?</hi> We may ſtate it more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How true Religion and Learning ought to be advanced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the meanes to advance piety, is to propagate the truth of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the meanes to make men rationall, is to advance the truth of Learning.</p>
               <p>To proſecute then the point in hand, we muſt enquire concerning theſe two Subjects, the which is moſt material to be advanced, and the way how it may either be advanced or prepared towards an advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at this time?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The advancement of Religion doth depend upon the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Miniſteriall Function, and this upon 3. Requiſites in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Their ſufficient qualification for their Charges.</item>
                  <item>2. Their painfulneſſe in their Charges.</item>
                  <item>3. Their orderly behaviour about the workes of their Charges.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For if Miniſters be able and well fitted for their work; if they be willing and diligent, to imploy that ſitneſſe and ability, and if they walk together united in that imployment, and do nothing unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame; nothing as to men will be wanting towards the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111996:4"/>of godlineſſe, and where God hath given all things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to produce an effect; we are to ſuppoſe he will not deny a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the production thereof.</p>
               <p>The ſufficient qualification of Miniſters, is the gift of Gods ſpirit in them; which men are to take notice of in the choyce and deſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of perſons to the Miniſtry in a twofold reſpect; the one in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Doctrine, the other to Practice.</p>
               <p>Their qualification in reſpect of Doctrine hath two parts. The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of knowledge and of utterance. Their qualification in reſpect of Practice hath alſo two parts. The one relates themſelves, which is their walking with God: The other the flock which is their ability to watch over others to lead them unto God.</p>
               <p>And although all theſe qualifications muſt be in every Miniſter in ſome competent meaſure; nor can he be counted fit for the Miniſtry, who is utterly deſtitute of any one of them: yet becauſe God hath diſtinguiſhed the Doctrinall gifts very much in their nature from the Practicall, and hath made their application and uſefulneſſe (though inſeparably joyned in the Church, and alike important to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole, yet) much diſtant in reſpect of their particular Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: therefore in the compleat adminiſtration of the whole Charge; there is one Paſtorall, and another Doctorall part of the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>And becauſe it is ſeldom found that men are equally gifted for both parts of the employment alike; and moſt commonly God doth fit one more eminently for the one, and another for the other part of the Charge: therefore in a numerous flock eſpecially, each part of the employment ought to have a particular Agent; who ſhould attend that part of the Miniſtry for which God hath more eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gifted him: yet both the Paſtor and the Doctor ſhould be but as one man in reſpect of the whole work towards the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Introduction then of a Lecturer (as he hath been called) in oppoſition to the Paſtor; or of a Paſtor in oppoſition to a Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, (which ſometime hath been much endeavoured) is one of the greateſt diſturbances of publique edification which can befall unto a Congregation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The paines which both Paſtor and Doctor ſhould take joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as being at once in the ſame employment and Miniſtry, is to labor in the word and prayer, as well in private as in publique.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The paines which the Paſtor ſhould take more diſtinctly (from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111996:5"/>which neither the Doctor is to be wholly exempt) is to viſit the flock in health and in ſickneſſe, to obſerve their wayes, to admoniſh to exhort, and to comfort them as occaſion is offered, and the paines which the Doctor ſhould take more diſtinctly (from which neither the Paſtor is wholly to be exempt) is to catechiſe the ignorant, to adde and increaſe knowledge to thoſe that have underſtanding by way of Conference, to handle matters of controverſie, to reſolve doubts, and to convince the gain-ſayers.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The orderlineſſe of their wayes in their employment is, no leſſe requiſite unto Publique edification; then either the fitneſſe of their qualification, or their painfulneſſe, and becauſe our preſent Miniſtrie hath been chiefly wanting in this; ſome one way, ſome another, therefore the confuſions which threaten our ruine are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come remedileſſe: Nay and the more Miniſters are able and painfull, the more they are hurtfull and pernicious to the building up of their flocks, and deſtructive to the advancement of Religion it ſelf, if they ſtand by themſelves. and walk without any co-ordination of endeavours towards their brethren, or neglecting the care of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall unity, runne into parties and diviſions; therefore if it ſhould ſo fall out (which God forbid) that the Miniſters cannot be brought upon ſpiritual grounds proper to their charge, to concur &amp; correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond with each other in ſome orderly courſes, it is to be wiſhed that by the Overſeers of the publick good. <hi>(Antiſtites Publici ordinis &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae)</hi> would by their authority under God, obleige them thereunto. For the Magiſtrate is accountable unto God, of all the publick wayes of men, committed to their charge: and if any ſhall walk in publick contrary to the rules of common Nature, and the principles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon, without controule, he ſhall anſwer for it unto God.</p>
               <p n="9">9. To remedie the diſorderlineſſe of thoſe that are in the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Function, or pretend unto it. Foure things from whence chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the diſorders ariſe, muſt be lookt into, and ſetled by ſome whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>The firſt, is the way of their entrance upon their places.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, the way of their maintenance in their places.</p>
               <p>The third, is the way of their employment about their works.</p>
               <p>And the fourth and laſt, is the ground of their relation, and way of their behaviour towards their neighbour workmen. In all theſe the want of a ſettled rule taken clearly from the word; the neglect of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111996:5"/>profeſſing that, wherein there is a known rule; and of practiſing that wherein there is an agreement about it: the affectation of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitted liberty to do all without a rule; and the naturall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men to be in a faction, and to act by a rule of contrarietie for a partie, have as ſo many roots of bitterneſſe ſprung up into the fruits of this diſorderlineſſe.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Concerning the calling, the maintenance, and the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Miniſters to and in their charges; there is ſome ground of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement to be found in the word; but concerning their ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and outward behaviour ſutable thereunto; how far humane authority ſhould intermeddle in the ſettlement of the firſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating of the ſecond; and in caſes of misbehaviour and offences either taken or given, how a competent Judicature to remove the ſame, is to be erected? Is the whole point of our difficulty. Yet theſe obſtructions of a ſettlement are not to be counted invincible if the preſident of publick order in humane affaires would on Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, appoint ſome to be controulers of the licentiouſneſſe of mens ſpirits in breaking the publick peace, that is to ſay, if the Magiſtrate could find out men free from partiality; and would authorize them with ſufficient inſtruction and limitations (leſt they ſhould abuſe their power) to bee a Committee to take away ſcandales, and to puniſh the Authors thereof; ſuch namely as by railing accuſations, ſhamefull calumnies, injurious practiſes, and diſorderly diſputations both in preſſe and pulpit blow the coales of our diſtempers; and ouerthrow the very Fundamentalls of Chriſtianity: If (I ſay) the Magiſtrate would fettle ſuch a Committee for the removing of ſuch ſcandalls by ſhaming the Authors thereof, it would certainly by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a check unto the ſpirit of malice, become at leaſt a healthfull preparative unto a further courſe of Reformation.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen that which is moſt materiall to be advanced in the profeſſion of Religion to make men godly, let us alſo take notice in brief of that which is materiall for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true Learning to make men rationall.</p>
               <p>Although men by nature have a reaſoning facultie, yet it is by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation and exerciſe, that they become Maſters of their reaſon to make right uſe of it. As then in that which concerns Religion, the Miniſteriall Function reſtored to its integrity, is the cheif outward meanes to advance Piety towards God; ſo in that which concernes Learning the Paedagogicall or Scholaſticall Function rightly ordered,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111996:6"/>will be the chief outward meanes, to perfect the uſe of right reaſon amongſt men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Scholaſticall Function next unto that of the Miniſtrie, and of the Magiſtracie, is moſt of all neceſſarie for the publick good, and the care of it to ſee it well ordered, is no leſſe the concernment of the Miniſtrie for the planting of piety then of the Magiſtracie for the planting of Moralitie; the ſeed which is firſt ſown will grow up ſooneſt, and hardly be ever rooted up. <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens, ſervabit odorem feſta diu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The end of Scholaſticall education, is to fit every one for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie and employment in the ſociety of men, whereunto by reaſon of his birth, he may have a right, or by reaſon of his naturall parts he may by others be called, or of his own accord lawfully apply himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. According to the difference of men in reſpect of their birth or naturall parts, and in reſpect of the employments whereunto they ought to be cultinated and made induſtriouſly rationall: a fourefold diſtinction either of Schooles, or of degrees of teaching and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the younger ſort is to be allowed and intended. Firſt, there ought to be a vulgar or plebean ſchool. Secondly, a ſchool for the Gentry and Nobility whereunto alſo the moſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſpirits of the vulgar ought to be received. Thirdly, a ſchoole of the Maſters of humane and naturall perfections. Fourthly, a ſchool of the Prophets, who are employed about divine and ſuper-naturall perfections. And the reaſon of this diſtinction of ſchools is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the nature of humane employments in all ſocieties, which reſpect either the body or the ſoule; in reſpect of the body the work of all men is either ſervile or commanding, and in reſpect of the ſoule, all the employment thereof, is either about humane or divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. Seeing then the vulgar ſort of men for the moſt part are borne to ſerve the common wealth in bodily matters; and the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Nobility are borne to have ſome command about theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, therefore as their induſtrie will have different ends and objects: ſo their rationall parts by their education ſhould be differently cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinated. Again, ſeeing a man lives not by the body alone, but chiefly by the ſoul, which is the proper ſeat of reaſon, and ſeeing the ſoule hath a twofold capacity, the one to apprehend naturall, the other ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall perfections; both which ought to be taught amongſt men, therefore the education of thoſe that may be made fit to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111996:6"/>theſe perfections, is a principle concenment of the ſociety of mankind. Whence, the two laſt degrees of ſchooles, are differenced from the two former in this mainly, that in theſe men are taught and educated to teach and educate others, and in thoſe men are only taught what they are to know and practice by themſelves.</p>
               <p n="6">6. From this diſtinction of ſchooles, or degrees of education, wee may gather this concluſion, tending to advance the publick good of a Reformation of learning; that if the two laſt ſorts of ſchooles, wherein the education of thoſe who are to teach others humane and divine knowledge, can be rightly ordered and conſtituted in this our age, the other two former in the next generation may be wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and when thoſe are effectually reformed then in one age more the body of the Nation will finde (by Gods bleſſing) the fruit of theſe endeavours.</p>
               <p>The ſchooles then which ſhould breed reformed Schoolmaſters, (that is, ſuch maſters of Arts, which ſhall be able in a reformed way to teach all humane and divine ſciences) will be the corner ſtone of this building. But to erect theſe Schooles we ſhall finde a threefold dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie. The firſt will be to find out and ſhew uncontrouleablely what the reformed way is, of teaching humane and divine ſciences, then when this way is found, the ſecond difficulty will be, to find Schoolmaſters which ſhall be willing to undertake the teaching by that way. Thirdly ſuppoſing that ſome will be found, The laſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie will be, how to propagate this way towards all by ſuch publick encouragements and demonſtrations of the uſefulneſſe thereof, as will take with every one.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Remedies to overcome theſe difficulties muſt in part be theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, All muſt be made ſenbſile of the abſolute neceſſitie of a Reformation in the way of ſchooling: and of the hurtfulneſſe of the preſent way thereof, in that it is very deſtructive unto all Piety and right Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the State ſhould be engaged to own affectionately the deſign of reforming Schooles upon this ground, becauſe the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof, is the ſeed-plot of all other Reformations, in the Church, in the offices of Judicature, and of other publick truſt, throughout the Common wealth; for it is evident, that ſeeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the corruptions which are practiſed in all theſe places (for which this Land doth now mourne) are brought into them original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111996:7"/>through the want of good education in piety and ſound learning and the ſtrength of naturall wickedneſſe not broken, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by evill habits in the very Schooles. Seeing (I ſay) this is ſo, it is evident that without the reformation of the wayes of education in the ſchooles, it will be impoſſible to bring any other reformation to any ſettlement or progreſſe in the whol Common-wealth; or leave the hopes thereof unto poſterity, becauſe partly the old corruptions and follies, partly worſer, will daily ſpring up amongſt men as long as they are not radically rectified, which can no where be done by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane induſtrie, but in the ſchooles.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the neceſſarie Reformation of ſchooles, muſt be ſet forth demonſtratively in three points. Firſt, in the reformation of the Schollars manners, and the inſpection to be taken of them in that regard. Secondly, in the reformation of the Arts and Sciences, which are to be taught them. And thirdly, in the reformation of the way of teaching the ſame.</p>
               <p>The manners of Schoollars, is the chief of al other things to be lookt into; the way therefore to exerciſe them in Piety, in Juſtice, in Temperance, in Faithfulneſſe, Truth and Diligence, is to be ſetled, and the inſpection over them in theſe things ſo regulated, that no faults, how wittily ſoever, and cunningly carried or covered; ſhould be connived at, without a juſt ſearch thereinto for diſcoverie, cenſure, and puniſhment. For if there be no courſe taken to root up the impiety, the folly, the injuriouſneſſe, violence, exceſſe, falſhood, untruth, and lazineſſe, which is in the diſpoſition of every child, he will not only grow ſtrong therein, but bold, to infect and provoke others thereunto; by which means he may bring not only his own ſoule unto damnation, but even ſpread the infection through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a whole nation. For the danger of ſuffering one to become a proſtitute Whore, mentioned <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.29. is the ſame proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally in all other ſinnes, if they be not ſpeedily prevented: <hi>One root of bitterneſſe will defile many.</hi> Heb, 12.15.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Arts and Sciences muſt be reformed in the ends and uſes, in the rules and precepts, and in the method and order thereof. As for the ends and uſes of all Arts and Sciences, they muſt be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured out, and ſubordinate by two rules. The firſt is, that of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The ſecond, is the common relief of mankind from outward miſeries. For what Art or Science ſoever, doth not advantage man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111996:7"/>either to bring him nearer unto God in his ſoule, or to free him from the bondage of corruption in his body; is not at all to be entertained, becauſe at the beſt it is but a diverſion of the mind from a profitable object to ſome vaine delight; which indiſpoſeth alwayes the ſoule to be converſant with things more ſeriouſly delightfull.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The Rules and Precepts of all Arts and Science, muſt be made demonſtrably true, and wholly ſuch, proper to the ends of the Science whereunto they belong, and are to be delivered, and prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily homogeneall to the univerſall matter thereof, and as ſuch in cleare tearms they ought to be delivered.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The method and order of Arts and Sciences muſt be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in two reſpects. Firſt, In the reſpect which one Art and Science hath to another, and in this regard they are to follow each other, according to the ſubordination of their ends and right uſes in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Secondly, In reſpect of the frame of every Art and Science with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf, as to the Rules and Precepts thereof; wherein ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſuch a dependance of the matter of each Science upon the end thereof, that all the cauſes whereby that end is made attaineable in that matter ſhould gradually be manifeſted.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, The reformed way of teaching thoſe Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thus rectified; beſides other properties, it muſt have theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Things neceſſary and univerſall muſt be firſt taught univerſally; and then things ſeverally uſefull and profitable to the ſeverall ends of education in the Arts and Sciences ſub-ſervient thereunto: where a maine rule is to be obſerved, that ſuperfluities be avoided. <hi>Sapientia prima eſt ſtultitia caruiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Every thing muſt be taught upon ſome fore-knowne Ground, as a conſequence thereof: the fore-known Grounds of all Rationall Matters, are outward ſenſe and fancy; and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Grounds of Divine Matters are Conſcience, and the ſence or experience of ones own thoughts in reference to God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Every thing whereof the ground is fore-known muſt be taught, firſt practically, and then Theoretically; Practically that is by an imitable example of that which is practicable therein, held forth by him that teacheth to the fancy of him that is taught: and then Theoretically, the ſame thing is to be delivered unto his judgement: that is, he is to be taught the Rule and Reaſon of that practice, to let him ſee how, and why it anſwers the end wherefore it is done.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111996:8"/>
               <p>Fourthly, The Principles of Piety ſhould be taught before the Principles of Reaſon in Practicall matters; and in Theoreticall the Rules of Rationall Truths, ſhould preceed the Rules of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Truths; for Divine Truths preſuppoſe right Reaſon, and exalt it to Objects above ſence and fancy, ſo then the will is firſt to be wrought unto the affections and duties of Piety, and then the underſtanding to the rules and exerciſes of Reaſon. Theſe two then, muſt gradually and hand in hand be led unto perfections, becauſe the will is a knowing, and the underſtanding a willing faculty, and both are the ſubjects of reaſon in their proper waies.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The application of Naturall Principles, and Reaſonings unto ſpirituall Objects, is a root of great confuſion in Sciences; but if the diſtinction of naturall and ſpirituall be duly kept, and the true Harmnony of the one to the other, with the proportion of reaſoning anſwerable thereunto be obſerved, that will ſet us againe aright. Therefore, as we are to be taught how ſpirituall things are to be diſcerned ſpiritually, and naturall things naturally, each in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, ſphear and way of knowledge according to his kind: ſo we are not to be left ignorant of the harmonicall coreſpondency which is between them, and the uſe of Reaſon therein. By which Rule, Schoole-Divinity being examined, will be found very light in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and in like manner, much of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſall Divinity, which is handled Scholaſtically in theſe our daies.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The whole way of teaching muſt be made free, ingenious, and delightfull; So then the mercinary way, whereunto Schoole-Maſters are forced, to betake themſelves for want of a competent livelyhood, ought to be remedied by ſome laudable proviſion, and rewards for induſtry: and on the other ſide, the ſervile and block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh way of training up Schollars for fear of puniſhment, to get cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine leſſons by rote, muſt be changed into a way of emulation and judgement.</p>
               <p>Other Remedies to theſe difficulties, together with a more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct deduction of the waies of Reformation might be offered, if either theſe times were ſeaſonable for particular undertakings in this kind, or if ſome ſpeciall Patron were found, who would out of true love to Piety and Learning, without the vanity of outward intereſts, countinance and ſupport ſuch enterprizes.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111996:8"/>
               <p>But ſeeing we ſee little or no hopes of any ſuch aſſiſtance, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we think it nor wiſdom, to proſtitute thoſe Propoſals without all appearance of ſucceſſe; yet becauſe on the other hand we ought not, we dare not, even in theſe times altogether deſpare of all favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable providences; therefore we are bound ſtill to maintaine ſome hopes, that in an age pretending ſo much to a Reformation, all aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will not be wanting, at leaſt ſo much as will further ſome ſuch preparative endeavours, as may very well ſtand with the diſtractions of the times, and may ſerve to open a doore to more effectuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings hereafter; therefore again we ſhall perſiſt to offer, cheifly to thoſe who are in Supreame authority, and have means for Publick uſes in their hands; the conſideration of two expedients, which may prove by Gods bleſſing even in this age, not only a hopefull, but an extraordinary ſuccesfull introduction to a future progreſſe in theſe times.</p>
               <p>The one is for the advancement of knowledge in the Orientall tongues, and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Myſteries.</p>
               <p>The other is for an Agency towards the advancement of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Learning.</p>
               <p>The firſt will be ſubordinate unto the meanes of ſetting forward Piety, the ſecond unto the waies of rationallity; The former will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a doore to many ſpirituall Graces, the latter to many temporall induſtries, as well as ſpirituall Graces; for this latter is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of all Objects of Piety, alſo as they are matters of Learning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Orientall Languages. <hi>The Myſteries of Jewiſh Learning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COncerning the Orientall Languages, and the writings of Jewiſh Myſteries, which are found therein; this is their prerogative be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Tongues and Writings of the World. That the firſt Oracles of God were uttered therein; that the fundamentall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of all true Worſhip and Religion towards God, were firſt made known, by them to the world, that the rules of Juſtice, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Prudency in occonomicall and civill Government amongſt men, were firſt expreſſed in them, and that the Hiſtory of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of all Nations, was never truly recorded but only by them; for it is unqueſtionably true, that at firſt all theſe things have been pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Jewes, and from them by degrees were propagated unto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111996:9"/>the reſt of the Nations. Therefore no doubt much reſpect is juſtly due unto thoſe Languages; and if their hidden treaſures were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, it is moſt certain, that a great addition of Wiſdom would thereby redound unto the reſt of the world. For although there were no more to be expected from thence, but a more diſtinct knowledge of the ancient wayes of God towards the firſt Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the world, and a more perfect inſight in thoſe Religious and Judiciall Statutes which he gave unto his own people, (of which we are much in the dark) and for which the other Nations did judge the <hi>Izralites</hi> a wiſe and underſtanding people,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6</note>) yet that alone ſhould be a ſufficient motive to cauſe us earneſtly to affect this ſtudy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which Chriſt doth uſe as an Argument to quicken his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples attention and diligence, to underſtand the hidden. Wiſdom of his Parables, ſhould in this caſe be a motive to cauſe us to deſire the knowledge of that which hath been of old. <hi>He ſaith, that he who is inſtructed unto the Kingdom of Heaven, ſhould be as a man who is a Houſe-holder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.52.</note> 
                  <hi>who bringeth out of his Treaſures things new and old.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although then we have the beſt and the new things of God, (wherein we that were laſt, are become firſt) yet we are not rightly fitted for his Kingdom, till we get into our Treaſures, the old alſo which we want. It is true indeed, that the new alone may fit us ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently for ſalvation in things privately for our ſelves neceſſary; but yet we are then but half inſtructed for the advancement of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the world, if we have not the old alſo.</p>
               <p>Therefore although the intrinſicall worth, and due eſteeme of the originall knowledge of ancient and hidden Truths, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Languages cannot be attained, ſhould ſuffice to encourage us unto this endeavour: yet this other inducement which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the Kingdom of God, ſhould have a ſtronger influence upon us, and will no doubt inforce this to the full, if it be rightly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; for we ſhall find upon due conſideration, that the new ſtore of the Kingdom, which we have in our Treaſury, is to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but an imperfect proviſion, ſo long as the old is not brought in alſo, and that the imperfection thereof (as to the building up of Chriſts Kingdom) is herein, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That it is defective in vertue by it ſelf alone, to propagate the knowledge of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> unto the apprehenſion of thoſe Nations, who are accuſtomed unto that which hath been of old.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111996:9"/>
               <p n="2">2. That the full confirmation of the Teſtimony of Jeſus, even to our ſelves that are <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhall not be compleated in a publick and Church way uncontrolably to the conviction of all, till both the Old and the New be brought forth together, to evidence the ſame truth in all ages of the world; if therfore either the propagation of the Goſpel effectually unto others, or the full confirmation of it to our ſelves (which are the great concernments that Chriſtians have upon earth) ſhould have any influence upon our deſires, then it will follow that we ought to endeavour the propagation of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe tongues; which will diſcover unto us the writings which containe the old Proviſion and Store of the Houſe of God, which are the true ancient Myſteries of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Learning, and whereby we ſhall be inabled, to diſcover unto them the writings which containe the New Proviſion, and Store of the Houſe of God, which God hath betruſted us withall in latter times to diſpence unto others.</p>
               <p>For firſt, how is it poſſible to have communication with thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in any thing without the knowledge of their Languages. And Secondly, How can their be any effectuall or rationall dealing with the <hi>Jews</hi> more eſpecially in matter of Religion, except we have a true and full in-ſight in their ancient, and they in our moderne Learning? Now that we are really oblieged, faithfully to endeavour, to have ſome communication &amp; dealings with them in matters of Religion, will evidently appear, if we reflect conſcionably upon the glory of God, which cannot otherwiſe be ſavingly manifeſted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Marke</hi> 16.15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48. <hi>Jer.</hi> 56.2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.</note> but in the face of Jeſus Chriſt upon the ſtate of their poor ſouls, who are our elder brethren in the Faith, as concerning the election for the Fathers ſake: and upon the diſcharge of our duty whereunto God hath called us in the holy profeſſion; which is to hold forth unto the world the word of life, to declare the teſtimony of Jeſus unto all creatures, and to publiſh even to the end of the earth, the deſtruction of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>Babylon</hi> as well as of the temporall, and Redemption of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> from their captivity. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. and 15.11. If (I ſay) we reflect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably upon theſe Motives, and conſider the opportunities which God doth put into our hands, to advance this endeavour, we ſhall find our ſelves highly obliged, to have ſome dealings with the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Nations, and cheefly with the <hi>Jewes</hi> that are amongſt men for the advancement of Chriſtianity; becauſe it is manifeſt to all, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111996:10"/>we have dealings with them in other things, even a free Commerce and Trade for worldly Commodities amongſt them all: and if we can make our addreſſes unto all of them in worldly things, how unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable will it be before God, if we ſhould not intend at all to make any application towards any of them in ſpirituall things, which things both they may receive from us and we from them, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable profit unto both, through the manifeſtation of Chriſt his glory in his Kingdom. For the benefit of the Trade will be recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, at leaſt very much for our advantage, by the confirmation of that Truth whereof God hath made us partakers above them; and according to the promiſes made of old unto them, ſeeing not only a clearer underſtanding of the things delivered by the ſpirit in the old Teſtament, will be granted by this meanes; but alſo many of the Myſteries of the new Teſtament, and cheifly that of the deſire of all Nations, the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> will be opened more fully to us by them, and by us unto them: becauſe it is evidently found of late by ſome that have traded, with their moſt ancient Rabbinicall writers, (men with them of unqueſtionable credit) that they ſpeake plainly from the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, the ſame Truths which are revealed unto us by the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they do give, not only unto us a manuduction to underſtand (for the ſtrengthning of our Faith) the harmony of the Old and New Teſtament more fully; but they alſo lay a ground of conviction for thoſe of their own Nation, to be dealt withall by us more effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the Demonſtration of the Truth, when we ſhall be able to back it with the Authority of their own Teachers, whom they dare nor contradict.</p>
               <p>There be ſome who have already gained much by this Trade, and if ſome reall courſe were taken to ſettle it amongſt us, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Authors to be Printed, and tranſlated, and in Publick view this truth would be made out unto all; that the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth teach nothing, but that Truth nakedly, which of old was darkly ſpoken of, and beleived by the cheif Doctors of the Jewes themſelves, and from the beginning by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This uſefulnes of the Orientall languages, and of the Jewiſh Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binicall writings, hath moved many in the reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to apply themſelves of late unto the ſtudy thereof, with much diligence and induſtry; the example therefore of others, together
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111996:10"/>with the like inclination in any here, raiſed upon the fore-named conſiderations, doth give us an encouragement to hope well of the ſucceſſe of this deſire. If then the countenance of Authority may be obtained, with maintenance to carry on the deſign, which by private Contribution hath been ſet up at <hi>London</hi> houſe, according to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition ſigned by the hands of many Miniſters, and others of the City well-affected, to the advancement of Learning and Piety: we would humbly move, that the ſettlement which ſhall be made, may be ſo conſiderable as to deſerve the name of a Colledge, for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Orientiall Languages and Learning; that is, that out of the reſerve which is kept for the advancement of Religion and Learning, ſuch an allowance may be made, as will maintaine ſome Profeſſors, and Students whoſe employment ſhould be,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To uphold Publickly a conſtant weekly Lecture in theſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</item>
                  <item>2. To attend the private inſtructions alſo, of ſuch as ſhall deſire the ſame.</item>
                  <item>3. To publiſh (a Printing Preſſe being erected which they ſhould ſet a work and over-ſee) and tranſlate ſuch Manuſcripts as ſhall be found moſt uſefull, for the propagating of the Truth amongſt thoſe Nations, and acquainting us with their Learning.</item>
                  <item>4. To advance the Printing of the new Teſtament into thoſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages at eaſie rates, to be made Common amongſt the Orientals and chiefly the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. To endeavour to facilitate the learning of thoſe Tongues, by the abridgment of Grammaticall intricaſies, and the naturall harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which is found between them.</item>
                  <item>6. To tranſlate alſo ſome of our Treatiſes into theſe Languages, to be imparted unto them for their converſion to the Truth.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Towards theſe employments, if the State would be pleaſed to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low but one thouſand pounds a year, and appoint Fee-offies in truſt, who ſhould be over-ſeers of the Colledge, and have power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the voluntary Contributions, as ſhall be given towards the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of theſe deſignes from time to time, (to maintaine the charges of Printing, to buy in Manuſcripts, and procure a Library of Orientall Bookes and to ſend Agents abroad, that they may trade in a Religious way with them) If (I ſay) ſuch an allowance were made for ſuch enployments and Fee-offies appointed; it is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111996:11"/>that the glory of God thereby be very much advanced, the honour of this Nation greatly upheld, and the reall intentions of Parliament, to propagate Religion, and Learning manifeſted to their praiſe, in this and after Ages.</p>
               <p>If ſuch a foundation were laid, and by the Countenance of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the work owned; then all thoſe that have been hitherto ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and well wiſhers to this deſigne here would be encouraged to enlarge themſelves, when they ſhould ſee that the enterprize would come to ſome perfection. Others from abroad will be drawn to a concurrence and communication in thoſe endeavours; the work might be carried on by a Correſpondencie; and the Honour of the whole ſucceſſe would be due to thoſe that ſhall lay the Foundation, whereupon others may add to the building. The diligence and zeale of the Romiſh <hi>Condare</hi> in their Colledge <hi>de Propaganda Fidem</hi> ſhould ſtirre us up to emulation, to doe our dutie in a better cauſe: for their Colledge is contrived only to maintain and educate Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to diſturb the peace of the reformed Churches, and propagate their own Superſtition; but this ſhould be to advance unto all, the meanes of Pietie and Learning which are concealed; and to uphold the fundamentalls of Chriſtianity, which are to be ſet up above hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Intereſts and particular Controverſies; wherein the deſigne will be ſo much the more ſubſervient unto Piety, by how much it will aime onely at the propagation and confirmation of things Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, and indifferently profitable unto all, which in the paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate fits of particular diſputes, are for the moſt part laid aſide and diſregarded, to the great prejudice of the truth of Chriſtianity; and the overthrow of Common edification. Therefore if by the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe things which may convict the Jewes of the truth of Chriſtianity; Chriſtians themſelves might get occaſion to conſider their common Intereſt, and therein be drawn to profeſſe a nearer Union then hitherto they have thought upon, this would be a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall happineſſe, which may poſſibly flow from this undertaking additionally. And we may promiſe to our ſelves ſome ſuch acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſucceſſe becauſe in good workes of a publique nature, which have an univerſall influence upon the whole ſubſtance of Religion;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.2.</note> all the advantages cannot be overſeen at once: They are like the trees of Paradice, which beare twelve manner of fruits, and yeeld their fruit differently every moneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:111996:11"/>
               <head>Of an Agencie for Advancement of Univerſall Learning.</head>
               <p>BY Univerſall Learning is meant a generall inſight and obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Objects and Faculties of Reaſon, and of the Wayes to bring the ſame to perfection by helping all mens Reaſonings as they are communicable and teachable unto others.</p>
               <p>By an Agency to advance this kinde of Learning is meant an Employment amongſt men, whereof the Scope and Aime ſhould be to diſcover to the Publike, and propoſe in particular to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one as occaſion ſhall be offered, all the advantages which are found and can be imparted unto all or any, for the improvement both of Reaſon it ſelf, and of particular Mens gifts towards a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good.</p>
               <p>This Agency is properly a Negotiation with the Society and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man, to take notice thereof in Reference to that Good, which may be found therein in a Publike or Private way; that Addreſſes may be had from one to another, to the end that the Defects of the one being ſupply'd by the other; The Rationall ways of Humane Communications may redound, as to the mutuall content of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, ſo to the Common Good of all Mankind.</p>
               <p>That ſuch an Agency may be ſet afoot, and ought to be intended for a Publike Good is evident, becauſe there is nothing more ſutable unto the Nature of Humane Society to make it compleat, then ſuch a kind of employment about thoſe Objects which are properly Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. We ſee that in all kinds of Societies there be ſeverall Agencies relating thereunto, and no Common-wealth can ſubſiſt without ſome of them; but theſe are all for particular Intereſts, which ſeldom are attein'd without ſome particular prejudice unto others, if not to the Generall diſadvantage of all. For from thence all our ſtrife in the world is begotten between States and States, and between one Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration and another in the ſame State: Now if we believe that there is any ſuch thing as the Nature of Man, wherein hee differs from beaſts; or that there ſhould be any Society between Man and Man upon the Grounds of a Common Intereſt; or that the ways of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb facs="tcp:111996:12"/>and the Communication thereof may be uſefull unto a Society of Men, and are worth the looking after, then it cannot be poſſibly doubted off, by any which is Rationall, that is a Man, whether any ſuch Agency may be ſet afoot and ought to be intended amongſt Men, for the Publike Good of their Society? The wilde beaſts of the Foreſt, and fiſhes of the Sea, every one preys for himſelf; and the ſtrongeſt devoures the weakeſt; ſo are the brutiſh men of the world to be counted worſe then they; who having forgotten the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Humanity, make none other uſe of their neerneſſe to others, of others ſociable inclinations towards them and of their own wit and ſtrength, but to prey upon their. Neighbours, to domineer over them, and devoure them for their private ends. The tamer and more docile Creatures made to ſerve man, joyn in herds and flocks, where all are as one; and one is as all; in reſpect of that which is uſefull unto them. To teach Man who is the Leader, and made to rule all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in all their Societies; to lead and rule himſelf by the ſociable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his diſpoſition, to finde the contentment of all his deſires &amp; advantages, rather in a Common then in a particular way. The wiſe State of <hi>Venice,</hi> the moſt Ancient and beſt ſetled republican Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the World; hath amongſt many other excellent Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this for one, that whoſoever doth ſhew unto that State any thing that may advance the Publike Good; ſhall receive a reward anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that which he doth offer: by this means the Aime of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good is upheld in the ſpirits of men; and Induſtry for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, (as it is a vertue; is encouraged and rewarded as it ought to be) by the Publike it ſelf. Whether there be any where elſe, in any Kingdom or State ſuch like Conſtitutions I know not, ſure I am in this place hitherto; Univerſall endevours and the thoughts of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Good free from partiality; have been lookt upon by many; and thoſe alſo in publike places rather as ridiculous whimſies &amp; projects, then matters worth any encouragement; but ſeeing we are now about a Reformation of our Ways, and neceſſitated to think upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Good, even for our preſervation from utter ruine and confuſion; and ſeeing ſome ſuch thing as the Advancement of Learning hath been oftner, and in a more publike Way, at leaſt mentioned in this
<pb facs="tcp:111996:12"/>Nation of late, then in former times, partly by the publication of thoſe excellent Works of the Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> which at ſuch a matter; partly by ſome reflection which the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons hath made that way, for the ſetting of a Gentleman apart for ſuch a uſe (although hetherto it hath been wholly fruitleſſe; and the party deſign'd for the ſervice left deſtitute of helps, yet) I ſay, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things are ſo, and chiefly ſeeing there is a Reſerve of Means purpoſely kept to be employ'd for the Advancement of Religion and Learning, and we are inform'd that an Ordinance is drawing up for the effectuall diſpoſall thereof towards thoſe ends; ſeeing (I ſay againe) theſe things are ſo, we ought not to deſpaire of ſome good iſſue at laſt; and therefore in reference to the Advancement of this Deſigne, which doth ſeeme already to be own'd and countenanc'd by Authority; I hope it will be counted no preſumption, if a Motion ſhould be made to make it more effectuall, then perhaps otherwiſe it is likely to prove, in caſe the Motion which men have ordinarily of that which is called Learning, and of the Advancement thereof be not rectified. We ſhall then (as concern'd in the Publike, uſe our rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall freedome to ſuggeſt thus much. That except the bounds of Learning be extended beyond the Univerſities; and be underſtood equall to the bounds of Schools, and to the care of Education, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent to a well Regulated Society of Men; And except the bounds of Schools be made as large as the borders of Rationality in Mankinde; we ſhall come very farre ſhort of that Aime, which ſhould be meant by the Advancement of Learning.</p>
               <p>It is far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to leſſen the honour due to the Univerſities; I rather ſtudy to increaſe the ſame; by making many Schools ſubordinate unto them, and ſubſervient unto their eminent ends; but I would not have that counted an honour due unto them, that they alone ſhould Monopolize all the Means of Learning, as if without the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities and Conſtitutions of old ſetled in them; there could be no truth of Learning, or right uſe of Reaſon advanced to attaine to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane or Divine Sciences elſwhere. I ſay, I would not have that to be counted their Honour, which is a Reall prejudice to the whole Common-wealth, and Society of Mankinde: therefore let no Art
<pb facs="tcp:111996:13"/>nor Science want his own Profeſſor, or Lecturer in the Univerſitie, nor either of the Univerſities want any of thoſe Profeſſors? Let none of thoſe Profeſſors want any encouragements, which may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to live comfortably, and proceed cheerfully and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to perfect the tasks of their profeſſion; Let (I ſay) all be done in this kinde that may be deſired, and nothing that may advance In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie neglected; but yet let not this be counted all, that is either Uſefull or Neceſſary to be done, for it will be found uſefull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the Foundations &amp; firſt Principles of Learning be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid in other Schools, which are to prepare Schollers for the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities; for if this be not intended with carefulneſſe, the publike Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of the Univerſities will hardly ever bring any thing to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; becauſe the ſuperſtructures which they are to labour in, towards their Schollers; will finde no bottome to ſupport them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will moulderaway without any benefit to the publike. But my purpoſe is not now to enlarge upon this ſubject; or to make out what the particular Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions of Schools ought to be; that may be done at another time more ſeaſonably; al that I would intimate at this time is this, that ſome proviſions will be neceſſary for inferiour Schools as well as for the Profeſſorſhips of the Univerſities, and that for the compleating of both the ſuperiour and inferiour Schools, towards the ends for which they are to be conſtituted; a publike Agencie for Univerſall Learning will be; if not even neceſſary, yet ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily uſefull, that without it there will be litle life and advancement towards any perfection in all the other Conſtitutions. For without ſome effectuall provocations, and grounds of vertuous emulations, mens ſpirits (chiefly when they are well provided for outwardly and feare no want) grow flat and ſluggiſh, they ſettle on their lees, and degenerate quickly. Nor is this all, why ſuch an Agency is requiſite; there is another thing of no leſſe, if not of greater importance then this, whereunto it will ſerve; and that is the proper end thereof, which is upon the diſcovery of Defects in publike or private ways of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of what kind ſoever; to intend a ſupply thereof, either by a free communication of ſuch advantages as are found uſefull to that effect; or by an enquirie and ſearch into the Means by which they may be
<pb facs="tcp:111996:13"/>found out if they be univerſally wanting. And again, upon the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of perfections attained unto, or probably attainable in any kind, and any where, amongſt the Learned at home or abroad; to ſpread and divulge the ſame to all ſuch as can any way improve them to a publike Good; or advantage their own Meditations by them. So that he being a Generall Inſpector of Mens Spirits, an Obſerver of their parts, an Overſeer of their ways in Learning, is to negotiate. for them and with them upon all occaſions, concerning every thing; which is deſirable towards the propagation of Divine or Humane Sciences. His trade is then to animate the Profeſſors of all Arts and Sciences, by a Correſpondency with all that are of any note, to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them by one another unto all Induſtry, and to gather up the fruits thereof, to be apply'd unto all the Schools for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Learning therein. How neceſſary this will be at the firſt conſtitution of Reformed Schools; and how unvaluably profitable, it will be at the progreſſe of the Reformation thereof; may be evident to all, that will conſider, That the chiefe cauſe of our diſtractions and moſt lamentable-diſorders in Learning is this; that there is no Concurrence in any common Aime, nor in any Rules which lead thereunto amongſt the Profeſſors of the ſame kinde of Learning; which makes every one of them walk by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves differently; ſolitarily: and without that helpe which their communications about the conquering of common difficulties would yield unto them: And this doth fall out, becauſe none doth ſolicit a Common Intereſt amongſt them, or giveth them occaſion to be engaged thereunto. For it is evident that men of themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are not averſe from Communications; becauſe when the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity thereof is offer'd unto them, we ſee it is embrac'd with joy; but they are unacquainted one with another, and a Centrall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Concurrence is wanting, which might make them meet one with another: This Center then ſhould be this Agencie, which ſhould be employ'd to diſcern in every kinde the ſeverall Abilities of Men &amp; their Undertakings to acquaint them with other mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the like abilities, labouring in the ſame ſubjects, either the ſame or a different way, that by mutuall acquaintance &amp; Conference
<pb facs="tcp:111996:14"/>their thoughts may be ripened, they may perfect, rectifie and benefit one another, and beat out the hidden paths of Truth, which in due time ſeaſonably may be publiſhed for the benefit of all. This Agency will not only impregnate the Spirits of fruitfull men with Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but will be as a Midwife to bring them to birth; and when they have brought them forth, it will addreſſe them unto the publike uſes whereunto they may be moſt ſerviceable for the Advancement of Learning. In a word briefly. What ever Neceſſity or uſe there may be of a Generall Solicitor in any publike Affairs, for the good of any Societie; that ſame neceſſity &amp; uſe is here to be found in this Agency for the Common-wealth of Learning in general, and more eſpecially for the Reformation and Conſtitution of Schools: and except they who ſhall be appointed by the State to intend the Advancement of Learning have ſuch an Inſtrument &amp; Agent at hand, who ſhal be able to impart unto them from all hands, that repreſentation of matters which ſhall conduce unto their Aime; their proceedings will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding imperfect, lame and defective; but if one be ſet thus apart. to become the Center of all ſuch Communications as ſhall conduce to their deſigne; from time to time, and all men of parts be drawn to contribute and ſuggeſt what they have gain'd by Meditation, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Experience to be uſefull towards the Advancement thereof, they may hope for a compleat eſtabliſhment of thoſe ways of Learning, which will make this Nation not only happy within it ſelf in one Age or two, but a Bleſſing unto others, and a Praiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Poſterity.</p>
               <p>And to bring all this ſuccesfully to paſſe, Theſe things are to be deſired in this Agencie.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1 <hi>THat the Agent already deſign'd by the Parliament, and long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe exerciſed in this way, and known to the chiefe men of parts at home and abroad, be ſpeedily provided for with a competent ſubſiſtance for himſelfe and family, that he may attend this worke without diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and with ſome allowance to defray the charges of his ordinary, and extraordinary Negotiation, of which he ſhall be accountable to the joynt Overſeers of the whole buſineſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2 <hi>That ſome Truſtees be appointed, Men of publique ſpirits, of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall
<pb facs="tcp:111996:14"/>parts and learning, of credit with all ſides, who ſhould together with and by the Agent, ſuper-intend the univerſall courſe, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Learning, that whilſt the Committee which is appointed for the diſpoſall of the reſerve, for the maintenance of Religion and Learning; ſhall be making the diſtribution of ſetled Salaries for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Profeſſors and School-maſters throughout the Kingdome, in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces moſt convenient, Theſe Truſtees may have</hi> 500 <hi>or</hi> 1000 <hi>lib. put into their hands as a yearly allowance from the State, towards the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wayes of Learning in generall, to be diſpos'd of by them in a more univerſall way, as the occaſions ſhall be offer'd unto them, advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to be employ'd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">3 <hi>Theſe Truſtees ſhould have power to receive voluntarie Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Legacies, which may be made from time to time by the wel-willers to the Meanes of Univerſall Learning; to ſee the ſame employ'd towards the ends for which they ſhall be contributed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="4">4 <hi>Thoſe Truſtees ſhould make a particular and exact deſcription both of the Univerſal Objects of Learning, about which they ſhould be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and alſo of the ways of their Conſultations, Cares, deliberation, and intendencie over the ſame, and of the managing of the Means betruſted unto them, which ſhould not be made common to every body, but onely communicated to all that are in places of Authority, that they may be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the uſefulneſſe of their employment.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="5">5 <hi>To theſe Truſtees, the common Agent, as one of them, ſhould be ſubſervient, and they ſhould be his Co-adjutors; ſo that he ſhould be oblig'd to make them acquainted with all his Negotiations, and upon mature deliberations follow their directions in the proſecution thereof.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6">6 <hi>They ſhould be Authoriz'd by the Supream Power of the Kingdom, to over-ſee all the Schools, to conſider all the Schoolmaſters, and their lives and abilities, and to furniſh them with helps as they ſhall ſee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the rectifying of their ways of Teaching and Educating.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="7">7 <hi>They ſhould have a regular correſpondencie with men of eminent and publique parts in forrain places by the means of their Agent, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover by them, and gain from them, all the feats of Learning which from time to time ſpring up amongſt them, that being found uſefull, they may be ſet afoot amongſt us, and accommodated unto our more profitable ways.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:111996:15"/>
                  <item n="8">8 <hi>To this effect a learned Secretary, one or more, for Latine, and other Vulgar Languages ſhould be entertain'd, to be under the direction of the Agent, according to the advice of the Truſtees, and ſome Clerks and Tranſcribers are to be had, which are skill'd to write in more Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges then one.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="9">9 <hi>The Hoſpitall entertainment of Travelling Learned Strangers, by whoſe means Intelligence may be gotten of things elſwhere moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, is to be allow'd as an extraordinary charge unto the Agent, who is to gain their acquaintance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="10">10 <hi>They ſhould have a peculiar Preſſe for Printing of things to be deſtributed and communicated to the Schools and Univerſities, or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally to the chiefe learned men of the Land, to poſſeſſe them with thoſe things which may ſeaſon their ſpirits with thoughts of a Publike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Other things ſubordinate unto theſe Ends, without which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie cannot be effectuall, and which are matters of coſt and charge are to be wholly referr'd unto the Truſtees, that the Means betruſted unto them may be beſtow'd to the beſt Uſes, which the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of times, places, and perſons do afford.</p>
               <p>Many excellent feats of Learning in Men, and in Manuſcripts lie dead and buried in oblivion, and cannot be brought to any perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for want of ſome patronage, but by the judgment of the Truſtees, and their faithfulneſſe to their Univerſall Aimes, and the diligence of their Agent, who is to bring all unto their hands, and by their advice to publiſh and communicate what is uſefull, this publike evill may be remedied, and a way open'd for the encouragement of Vertue and Induſtry, in the beſt and moſt eminently uſefull Objects of Divine and Humane Knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111996:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
